Guide to the Leonard Solomon Silk papers, 1929-1995 and undated, bulk 1950-1985 RL.01187
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leonard Solomon Silk papers
1929-1995 and undated, bulk 1950-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Silk, Leonard Solomon, 1918-1995
RL.01187
544.7 Linear Feet
The papers of noted economist Leonard Silk span his entire career and include correspondence files; printed material such as periodicals and reports; research or subject files; newspaper clippings files; drafts of writings, including Silk's books, New York Times news columns, editorials, speeches, lectures, book reviews, and essays. There are also papers and reprints by Silk's colleagues; organizations files; publicity and informal photographs of Silk; financial documents; economic data; some teaching materials such as reading lists; and theses and dissertations (including Silk's own thesis on Swedish post-war housing, 1947). The collection also contains groups of cards, notes, memos, calendars and agendas. Silk's papers are a vast and rich resource for learning about the intersection of politics, economics, and popular opinion in the 20th century, U.S. fiscal policies, global economics, and specific topics as unemployment, inflation, banking, Keynesian economics, markets and marketing, the economies of Asian countries, and many other subjects. A more detailed original paper inventory is available in the library; in it significant portions of the correspondence are listed at the item level, including correspondents' names.
Approx. 326,732 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Leonard Silk papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from the University of Wyoming in 2005 and 2008.
Biographical Note
Leonard Solomon Silk, a journalist of economics, was born on May 15, 1918 in Philadelphia, and passed away in 1995 in Montclair, New Jersey. He entered Dickinson College in Pennsylvania in 1936 and transferred to The University of Wisconsin on a scholarship the following year. There he began his journalistic career, editing the humor magazine Octopus. He also became influenced by the cutting-edge economics department, and professors such as Selig Perlman. Silk entered Duke University in 1940 for graduate study in economics; his mentor at Duke was international economist Calvin Bryce Hoover. His graduate study was interrupted during World War II when he enlisted in the Army Air Forces. He worked as a Morse code operator in Alaska, but also wrote for Yank and other Army publications. In this capacity, he covered the 1945 founding conference of the United Nations in San Francisco. Upon his return to graduate study in 1946, he travelled to Sweden to study the Swedish housing system. He published an article on this research in Fortune magazine; a longer version of which became his Ph.D. thesis and subsequently his first book, Sweden Plans for Better Housing (1948), published by Duke University Press.
Silk is most well known as a columnist and editorial writer for The New York Times and Business Week. He was one of the first journalists known for making complex economic issues understandable to the average reader. He became a full-time columnist for The New York Times from 1976-1993 and published a column twice weekly in the business pages under the Economic Scene rubric. In later years he also frequently wrote major news stories on economic issues.
In addition to his journalistic work, Silk taught economics at the University of Maine, Simmons College in Boston, the University of Oslo, and Pace University. He was a Senior Research Fellow on the United Nations for the Ralph Bunche Institute at the City University of New York, and a Senior Fellow of the Brookings Institution. He worked for the federal government in various positions such as a housing expert and an economist for the United States Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO).
Silk expanded much of his journalistic research into books; his most well known are Economics in Plain English (1978), Economics in the Real World (1984), and The American Establishment.
Silk was drawn to economics by the Great Depression. During his undergraduate study at the University of Wisconsin, he was influenced by Keynesian theory and recently popularized views that economists should study micro-economics and not just macro-economics. Eventually Silk moved away from Keynesian theory, but advocated both government regulation and deregulation based on the particular economic situation. He viewed economics as a branch of philosophy and believed that economics should improve the quality of life for people, especially the disadvantaged.
Collection Overview
The papers of Leonard Silk span his entire career, and are arranged by original accessions, within which there are divisions by format,assembled by Silk. Most but not all accessions are described in this collection guide. The largest one is numbered 6096 and comprises over 80 large boxes.
There are many format divisions, and they typically include correspondence files; printed material such as periodicals and reports; research or subject files; newspaper clippings files; drafts of writings, including Silk's books, news columns, editorials, speeches, lectures, book reviews, and essays; papers and reprints by Silk's colleagues; organizations files; publicity and informal photographs of Silk and others; financial documents; economic data such as forecasts and tables, much of it reported by the U.S. government; some teaching materials such as reading lists; and theses and dissertations (including Silk's 1947 thesis on Swedish housing policies). There are also groups of cards, notes, memos, calendars and agendas, and some minutes of meetings relating to organizations with which Silk was involved.
Leonard Silk's papers are a vast and rich resource for learning about the intersection of politics, economics, and popular opinion in the 20th century. Specific topics include U.S. fiscal policies; global economics (starting with materials on post-World War II Europe); trends in social institutions in the U.S.; and other economic topics as American business, unemployment, inflation, banking, macroeconomics and Keynesian economics, markets and marketing (pharmaceutical and tobacco, among others), the economies of Asian countries such as Japan, and many other subjects.
A more detailed original paper inventory is available in the library; in it, significant portions of the correspondence are listed at the item level, including correspondents' names; separated book titles are also listed individually. Many groups of other materials, however, are described only by number of pieces.
In the correspondence files, many of them arranged in chronological order, the majority of the letters are addressed to Silk, but there are also some written by him. Significant correspondents include writers and journalists as well as well-known political figures and economists too numerous to mention. A search using key words may be helpful in locating particular individuals. Again, the original paper inventory contains the names of hundreds of individual correspondents.
The largest group of materials in the collection consists of print items. Silk assembled extensive research files of clippings, articles, periodicals, reports, government publications, and reprints. All of these supported his current research interests, which ranged widely but chiefly focused on macroeconomics, Keynesian economic theory, economics for the social good, and banking and finance. He also set aside pamphlets, tables and charts, and even maps related to his travels.
Collection Arrangement
The collection has been given basic processing and is in the original order as received by the University of Wyoming from where it was transferred. The largest divisions represent additions to the Silk Papers, numbered by the University of Wyoming and dated, each of which is made up of format groupings such as correspondence, reports, and subject files, which appear randomly throughout each addition. Within those groupings there is often an original alphabetical order, particularly for subject files and correspondence. Keyword searching can be used to uncover specific topics or names in this large collection. Note that portions of the collection accessions are not described in this collection guide. The papers are in the queue to be fully processed by library staff.
Gaps in the box number sequence come from print materials that were separated for the Perkins Library general collections, and are no longer housed with the manuscript collection. See the administrative sections at the beginning of this collection guide for more information.
Separated Material
At the University of Wyoming, and later, upon arrival of the collection at Duke, boxes of selected print material such as books and pamphlets were separated from the personal papers represented in this collection guide. At Duke, large groupings of print material have been transferred to the Perkins Library general collections or to the holdings of the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Gaps in the box number sequence reflect these separated boxes. The original paper finding aid lists most but not all of the books originally in the collection by title. Please contact Research Services in the Duke David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library for assistance in locating materials.
Related Material
Arthur F. Burns Papers, 1929-2003 and undated, bulk 1953-1981 (U.S. economist and consultant to Federal Government)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Banks and banking -- United States; Economics -- Public Opinion; Economics -- Study and teaching; Economists -- Correspondence; Fiscal policy -- United States; Fiscal policy -- United States -- Public Opinion; Finance -- United States; Journalists -- United States; Keynesian economics; Macroeconomics; Mass media and economics; Unemployment -- United States; United States -- Economic conditions -- 20th century; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century -- Press coverage; Photographs; New York Times; Silk, Leonard Solomon, 1918-1995; Silk, Leonard Solomon, 1918-1995
- Accession 84-01-01, 1967-1982 and undated, 8 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Print materials on economics and finance, notebooks kept by Silk related to peer reviews for honors and prizes; and many subject files on economics and finance topics. There are also folders of professional correspondence, chiefly from the 1970s and 1980s.
  Gaps in the box number sequence reflect separated print material. See the administrative sections at the top of this collection guide for more information. A more detailed original paper inventory is available in the library; in it significant portions of the correspondence are listed at the item level, including correspondents' names.
  - Printed Material (Box 3)
    - Periodicals on finance and economics, including Canadian titles, 15 items (Box 3)
  - Notebooks
    - Pulitzer Prize Journalism recommendations, 1970, 1973-1974, 1976, 4 vols. (Box 3)
    - Pulitzer Prize nominations, journalism and letters summary, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Pulitzer Prizes, secretary's report, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Committee on the Future, reports, 1967, 6 vols. (Box 3)
    - Economics for Journalists nominations, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Subject Files, Economic Indicators-Reports (Box 5)
    Subject file folders containing primarily printed materials and some manuscripts and notes. Titles are original. Arranged in original alphabetical order.
    - Economic Indicators (Box 5)
    - Economics (Box 5)
    - Economics/education (Box 5)
    - Economics/general (Box 5)
    - Education (Box 5)
    - Kemp, Jack/Kreps, Juanita - nomination (Box 5)
    - Lehrman Institute, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - National Bureau of Economics Research (NBER), 1980 (Box 5)
    - News releases, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Planning: policy news (Box 5)
    - Reagan budget, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Salomon Bros., 1981 (Box 5)
    - William Schuman (Box 5)
    - Speeches/Remarks (Box 5)
    - Stocks, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Third world, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Trade, 1979 (Box 5)
    - U.N. Institute for Training and Research, 1979 (Box 5)
    - University of Chicago, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Productivity (Box 5)
    - Reports and brochures (Box 5)
  - Printed Material: U.S. and foreign titles on economics, 29 items (Box 6)
  - Notebooks: Public Interest Profiles (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets and Other Printed Material, 10 items (Box 6)
  - Speeches, 13 items (Box 6)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Silk, Leonard, 1977-1978, 1980-1981, 8 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Hellman, Lillian, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Middleton, D., 1980 (Box 7)
    - Mitgang, H., Jan.-Dec., 1980 (Box 7)
  - Subject Files, AEA-Employment
    Primarily printed material and some manuscripts and notes.
    - American Economic Association, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Arthur D. Little, Inc., 1980 [on banks?] (Box 7)
    - Committee for Economic Development (Box 7)
    - Economic Outlook, 1979 (Box 7)
    - Employment (Box 7)
  - Notebooks
    - Snyder, J.M., The Way of the Hunter Warrior (Box 7)
  - Subject Files, Energy-Universities (Box 8)
    - Energy (Box 8)
    - Ernst, Dr. H.B., 1981 (Box 8)
    - Ford Foundation, 1979 (Box 8)
    - France (Box 8)
    - Germany (Box 8)
    - Japan (Box 8)
    - Oil (Box 8)
    - Tax Incentives, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Townsend-Greenspan, 1981 (Box 8)
    - U.S. Competitiveness (Box 8)
    - Universities, Misc., 1981 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 32 items (Box 8)
  - 1977 Citibank calendar (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1976-1982, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Documents, Published: U.S. and foreign, economics, 41 items (Box 10)
  - Subject files, various, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Legal Documents, contract for speaking engagement (Box 10)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 27 items (Box 10)
  - Correspondence (Box 15)
    - 1972-1982, 7 folders (Box 15)
  - Published Documents
    - U.S. - five pieces on economics (Box 15)
  - Interviews
    - Hayek and Samuelson, 2 items (Box 15)
  - Pamphlets and Other Printed Material, 60 items (Box 15)
  - Periodicals, 19 items (Box 15)
  - Photographs and related material (Box 15)
  - Reprints, 11 items (Box 15)
  - Speeches, 23 items (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 21 items (Box 15)
  - Subject Files (Box 16)
    Folders are arranged in random order and contain correspondence, notes, clippings, manuscripts, and other items assembled by Silk.
    - Capitalism (Box 16)
    - Ethics (Box 16)
    - Silk/Japan (Box 16)
    - IMF - 1975 (Box 16)
    - Establishment/CFR (Box 16)
    - New York Times - articles, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Sloan advisory board meeting - Feb. 21, 1976 (Box 16)
    - Vietnam, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - 1980s (Box 16)
    - Burns, Arthur (Box 16)
    - Conference board (Box 16)
    - Conference board meeting (Box 16)
    - Is Economics a Science? (Box 16)
  - Newspapers, Newspaper and Magazine Clippings (Box 16)
  - Notebooks
    - Research notes by Leonard S. Silk (Box 16)
    - Kami, M., Managing the Future - Executive Workbook (Box 16)
- Accession 84-03-08, 1936-1983 and undated, 14 boxes
  Chiefly research files of various kinds, including subject files, periodicals, reports, clippings files, pamphlets and other printed material, and some correspondence.
  - Subject Files, 1981-1982, Budget-Wright (Box 3)
    - Budget (Box 3)
    - Social Security (Box 3)
    - Speeches/talks (Box 3)
    - Supply-side economics (Box 3)
    - Political Science Quarterly (Box 3)
    - Productivity (Box 3)
    - Profit (Box 3)
    - Rational Expectations (Box 3)
    - Reaganomics (Box 3)
    - Reindustrialization (Box 3)
    - Yale (Box 3)
    - Depression (Box 3)
    - Duke University (Box 3)
    - Economics (Box 3)
    - Foreign policy assn. (Box 3)
    - Forrester, Jay W., Mass Institute Technology (Box 3)
    - Future (Box 3)
    - TIP (Box 3)
    - Universities/misc. (Box 3)
    - Urban (Box 3)
    - Venture services, Weaver, James (Box 3)
    - Washington Speakers Bureau (Box 3)
    - Weston, Robert (Box 3)
    - Welfare (Box 3)
    - Wright Investors, Robert Wright (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1970s and 1980s
    - Economics, 3 or 4 file folders (Box 3)
  - Periodicals, 1978-1982, 18 items (Box 3)
  - Books (Box 4)
    - Ohlin, B., Interregional and International Trade, 1936 (Box 4)
    - Wiegland, G. C., Toward a New World Monetary System, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Research, 1980
    - Ronald Reagan (Box 4)
    - Economy (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1970s and 1980s
    - Economics, approximately 12 file folders (Box 4)
  - Books (Box 6)
    - Leamer, L. E., et al., Suggestions for a Basic Economics Library, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Silk, L., et al., The World of Economics, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Silk, L., Readings in Contemporary Economics, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 6)
  - Research, 1972-1976
    - Pieces - Economics (Box 6)
    - National Science Foundation (Box 6)
    - Markets (Box 6)
    - Additional Readings (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, circa 1970s, 4 file folders (Box 6)
    Loose, some related, mostly economics, also clippings and newspapers.
  - Periodicals, 1977-1978, 4 items (Box 6)
  - Research, circa 1980s, 4 file folders (Box 7)
    Topics generally political.
  - Periodicals, 1979-1980, 2 items (Box 7)
  - Research, 1982 (Box 9)
    - International risk (Box 9)
    - Industrial policy (Box 9)
    - Hot Line Cares, Inc., Flores, Ralph (Box 9)
    - Haverford College (Box 9)
    - Hart, Sen. Gary (Box 9)
    - Group of Thirty (Box 9)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1983, 22 items (Box 9)
  - Periodicals, 1983, 8 items (Box 9)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1977-1979, 42 items (Box 14)
  - Periodicals, 1978, 2 items (Box 14)
  - Government Documents, 1978-1983, 13 items (Box 16)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1983 (Box 16)
  - Periodicals, 1982-1983, 6 items (Box 16)
  - Reports, 1982-1983, 11 items (Box 16)
  - Speeches, 1982-1983, 8 items (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1983, 2 file folders (Box 19)
  - Research, 1980
    - S and S, Living with Economics (Box 19)
    - American Economics Association (Box 19)
  - Notebooks, circa 1980s
    - Economics for the Perplexed, Notes and Drafts (Box 19)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1980-1983 (Box 19)
  - Periodicals, 1976-1978, 6 items (Box 19)
  - Reports, 1980-1982, 11 items (Box 19)
  - Biographical Information, 1979 (Box 20)
  - Research, circa 1970s
    - Leonard Silk - schedules (Box 20)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, circa 1970s (Box 20)
  - Periodicals, 1977-1979, 7 items (Box 20)
  - Reports, 1977-1979, 7 items (Box 20)
  - Research, 1983 (Box 21)
    - Leonard Silk, The New York Times (Box 21)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1983
    - Leonard Silk columns (Box 21)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1982-1983, 22 items (Box 21)
  - Periodicals, 1978-1983, 7 items (Box 21)
  - Reports, 9 items (Box 21)
  - Research, 1982 (Box 22)
    - Cancun, Mexico (Box 22)
    - Committee for Economic Development (Box 22)
    - City University of New York (Box 22)
    - Rustow, Prof. D.A. (City University of New York) (Box 22)
    - Clarke, Stephen (Box 22)
    - Cleveland, Ohio (Box 22)
    - Compumetrics, Inc. (Box 22)
    - Pace University - Instructor's roster and file (Box 22)
  - Government Documents, 1976 (Box 22)
  - Periodicals, 1978-1982, 2 items (Box 22)
  - Reports, 1982-1983, 4 items (Box 22)
  - Research, 1982 (Box 27)
    - National defense (Box 27)
    - Oil (Box 27)
    - Oppenheimer holdings (Box 27)
    - Bator (Box 27)
    - Baumol, William J. (Box 27)
    - Biz (Box 27)
    - Brochures/magazines (Box 27)
    - Brookings (Box 27)
    - Resumes (Box 27)
    - Social security-retirement (Box 27)
    - Royatyn, Felix G. (Box 27)
    - Rukeyser, Louis, Business Journal (Box 27)
    - Schroeder study (Box 27)
    - Schuman, William (Box 27)
    - Shubik, Martin (Box 27)
    - Japan (Box 27)
    - Islam (Box 27)
    - Jobs (Box 27)
    - Lehman Brothers (Ball, George) (Box 27)
    - Meyers, Bernard (Box 27)
    - National Conference of State Legislatures (Box 27)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1983, 3 items (Box 27)
  - Periodicals, 1983, 5 items (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 28)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1983, 6 items (Box 28)
  - Periodicals, 1973-1983, 6 items (Box 28)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 29)
  - Research, 1982
    - Quaker (Box 29)
    - Public misc. (Box 29)
    - Agency for International Development (Box 29)
    - Arno Press (Box 29)
    - Articles (Box 29)
    - Regulation (Box 29)
    - Pace University, 2 files (Box 29)
    - Budget Cuts (Box 29)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1979, 6 items (Box 29)
  - Periodicals, 1983 (Box 29)
  - Reports, 1982-1983, 11 items (Box 29)
- Accession 85-02-28, 1952-1985, and undated, 15 boxes
  Chiefly printed material, particularly periodical issues of interest to Silk, clippings files, some of his own columns, and economics reports. Also includes drafts of Silk's writings and files of correspondence.
  - Directories, 1983-1985 (Box 12)
    - International Franchise Association, and Columbia Business School faculty, 2 items (Box 12)
  - Manuscript, 1985
    - Walter, I., Deregulating Wall Street, draft (Box 12)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, economics, 1984, 4 items (Box 12)
  - Periodicals, economics, world news, 1982-1984, 9 items (Box 12)
  - Reports, economics, 1978, 1984, 5 items (Box 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Silk, Leonard, New York Times book reviews and regarding Argentina (Box 19)
  - Pamphlets and other printed material, 1952, 1978, 2 items (Box 19)
    Regarding economics and the University of Chicago Graduate School.
  - Periodicals, 1963, 1981-1984, 6 items (Box 19)
    Chiefly regarding economics.
  - Program, 1970
    - Allied Social Science Associations (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 21)
    - Business, between Leonard S. Silk and associates; economic issues and invitations to lecture (Box 21)
  - Document, 1982
    - United Nations; World Economic Recovery (Box 21)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1975-1980
    - Silk, L., New York Times (Box 21)
  - Subject files, 1982-1984
    - Regarding economics, printed material (Box 21)
    - Computer service industry (Box 21)
    - Conference/miscellaneous (Box 21)
    - Duke University (Box 21)
    - Economics, 4 file folders (Box 21)
    - Lehman Brothers, Kuhn Loeb (Box 21)
    - National Conference of State Legislators (Box 21)
    - New York Stock Exchange (Box 21)
    - New York University (Box 21)
    - Pace University/term papers (Box 21)
    - Public miscellaneous (Box 21)
    - Speeches/talks (Box 21)
    - University of Chicago (Box 21)
    - University of Wyoming (Box 21)
    - Wharton (Box 21)
    - World Bank (Box 21)
  - Address, 1978 (Box 22)
    - Ryrie, W., The World Monetary Scene (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 22)
    Business: to Leonard S. Silk from associates; economic issues and invitations to lecture.
  - Dissertation
    - Vogel, D., Contemporary Criticism of the Business Corporation: A Historical and Cultural Critique, 1974 (Box 22)
  - Document
    - United States; economic stabilization policies, 1978 (Box 22)